Finding Aid for Genevieve Gillette Papers 1914-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Genevieve Gillette Papers 1914-1987, 1951-1980
Gillette, Genevieve, 1898-
1 oversize folders
10 linear feet
Ann Arbor, Michigan, Landscape architect, speaker and lobbyist on behalf of conservation and beautification, president of the Michigan Parks Association, and member of the Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation and Natural Beauty during the Johnson Administration. Correspondence, reports, oral history interviews, and other materials concerning her interest in state and national conservation legislation; and photographs.
851409 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Genevieve Gillette (donor 4833 ) in periodic accessions between 1969 and 1987.
The collection is open for research.
Genevieve Gillette was instrumental in the development of Michigan's state park system. In 1959 her interest in developing outdoor recreation opportunities for the people of Michigan led her to help establish the Michigan Parks Association. Over the following decade Gillette led the association to fight for the establishment of Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore and other national and state parks, as well as to lobby for better funding for the state park system. As a result of her work, President Johnson appointed Gillette in 1966 to the Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation & Natural Beauty.
Emma Genevieve Gillette (she did not commonly use her first name), was born May 19, 1898 in Lansing, Michigan, the daughter of David Commodore and Kittie Beal Gillette. Gillette grew up on a farm near Dimondale, Michigan, and in 1916 entered the Michigan Agricultural College where she studied horticulture and landscape architecture. She graduated in 1920, the only woman graduate in the school's first landscape architecture class. One of her classmates, Percy J. Hoffmaster, became superintendent of Michigan's state parks and later director of the Michigan Department of Conservation.
After graduation Gillette worked with the Chicago landscape architect Jens Jensen for a time, then moved to Detroit in 1924 where she established her own practice. (She moved to Barton Hills, Michigan, in the 1940s.) Among the projects she worked on were Lakeland, Florida (1925); Westacres, a greenbelt-type development in Oakland County, Michigan (1932); Albion College (from the 1940s); and Big Rapids, Michigan (from 1955).
At the same time her architectural practice was developing, Gillette began assisting Hoffmaster as a volunteer, helping to select sites for Michigan state parks. Her volunteer work was done through a variety of organizations, many of which Gillette helped to found, including the Michigan Horticultural Society (1930), Detroit Rose Society (1930), Michigan Botanical Club (1937), Michigan Natural Areas Council (1940s), and Michigan Parks Association (1959). In addition to these voluntary organizations, Gillette worked through several government bodies, including the Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority (early 1940s), White House Conference on Natural Beauty (1965), (Michigan) Governor's Conference on Natural Beauty (1965), Michigan Wilderness and Natural Areas Advisory Board (1972-1980), and Washtenaw County Parks and Recreation Commission (beginning 1973) and its predecessor organizations beginning in the early 1960s.
After Hoffmaster's death in 1951, Gillette continued to support the development of Michigan's park system, and began to take on more of the leading role that she felt had been vacated by the death of her friend. Under the umbrella of the Michigan Parks Association, she lobbied for parks on three main fronts: First, for the acquisition of new parklands, using both state and federal funds. This work concentrated on Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore, Sylvania Recreation Area and McCormick Experimental Forest in the Ottawa National Forest, and Mill Creek Metropark west of Ann Arbor; Second, for the preservation of existing parks, especially Porcupine Mountains State Park, the Rouge River floodplain near the University of Michigan--Dearborn, and federal wilderness areas;Third, for development of new sources of funds for the state parks. In the 1960s this work concentrated on the federal Land and Water Conservation Fund and a state recreational bond issue.
In addition to her work for Michigan state parks, Gillette's general interest in landscape architecture led her into the field of scenic roads and highway beautification, which she developed after being appointed to President Johnson's Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation & Natural Beauty in 1966.
During the 1970s and 1980s Gillette's work slowly declined even while she received more and more acclaim for her accomplishments. She died May 23, 1986.
The Genevieve Gillette collection documents Gillette's concern for the development of Michigan's parks and outdoor recreation opportunities, and her work to promote scenic roads in Michigan and nationwide.
Among the issues most fully documented are the fight to establish and develop Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore, acquisition and development of Sylvania Recreation Area and McCormick Experimental Forest, threats to wilderness in the Porcupine Mountains State Park, the controversy over the proposed Mill Creek Metropark, the financing of Michigan's state park system, especially the 1968 campaign to approve recreation bonds, and the development of the Rouge River floodplain near the University of Michigan--Dearborn.
The work of the Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation & Natural Beauty (1966-1968), the Michigan Parks Association (1959-1975), and the Washtenaw County Parks and Recreation Commission and predecessor organizations (1960-1974) are also documented.
The collection includes very little documentation of Gillette's professional work as a landscape architect, and includes almost nothing relating to her parks and recreation work before the late 1950s.
The collection is divided into three major series--Personal, Correspondence, and Topical file--and two small series--Photographs, Audio tape cassettes.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Conservationists--Michigan.; Cyrus H. McCormick Experimental Forest (Mich.); Gillette, Genevieve, 1898-; Isle Royale National Park (Mich.); Michigan. Dept. of Conservation.; Michigan Parks Association.; Mill Creek Metropark (Mich.: Proposed); National parks and reserves--United States.; Natural resources--United States.; Oral history.; Parks--Michigan.; Pictured Rocks National Lakeshore (Mich.); Porcupine Mountains State Park (Mich.); Roads--United States.; River Rouge (Mich.); Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.); Sylvania Recreation Area (Mich.); United States. Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation & Natural Beauty.; Westacres (Mich.); Women conservationists--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Altman Miller Company (Lansing, Mich.); Business enterprises--Michigan--Lansing.; Cambridge Junction (Mich.); Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Lansing.; Gillette, Genevieve, 1898-; Gillette family.; Interiors.; Lyndon, Park (Mich.); P.J. Hoffmaster State Park (Mich.); Parks--Michigan.; United States. Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation & Natural Beauty.; Walker Tavern (Cambridge Junction, Mich.); Westacres (Mich.)
Sound Recordings
Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Conservationists--Michigan.; Frank, Patricia M.; Gillette, Genevieve, 1898-; Michigan. Dept. of Conservation.; Michigan Parks Association.; National parks and reserves.; Natural resources.; Oral history.; Parks--Michigan.; Porcupine Mountains State Park (Mich.); Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.); Women conservationists--Michigan.
Contributors:
Freeman, Orville L.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Jensen, Jens, 1860-1951.; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Personal
  The Personal series (Box 1) includes biographical sketches, clippings, and information about awards received, but perhaps the most valuable part of the series is a set of transcripts of oral history interviews made in the 1970s.
  - Autobiographical writings (Box 1)
  - Biographical sketches (Box 1)
  - Christmas letters 1958-1969 (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - 1920s-1930s undated (Box 1)
    - 1940s-1960s (Box 1)
    - 1970s (Box 1)
    - 1980s (Box 1)
    - Obituaries (Box 1)
  - Coat-of-arms (Box 1)
  - Honorary degrees and awards
    - Albion College 1966 (Box 1)
    - Holiday Magazine 1968 (Box 1)
    - Michigan State University 1969, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Park Lyndon dedication 1966, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Naturalist notebook circa 1914 (Box 1)
  - Oral history 1971-1972
    (tapes located in Box 10)
    - Frank report, tapes 1-5 (Box 1)
    - Summaries, tapes 16-31 (Box 1)
    - Transcripts, tapes 2-4, 16A-16F, 17-31, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - Sketches (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (Boxes 2-4) includes correspondence relating to all the topics documented in the collection. It is arranged in a chronological sequence, except that correspondence with Jens Jensen is separated in 2 folders (Box 2). Most attachments referred to in correspondence have been separated and are found in the Topical file. Because correspondence is separate from the Topical file, researchers must search both series to find all the collection's material on a topic. Generally the amount of correspondence relating to a topic is roughly proportional to the amount of non-correspondence material found in the Topical file.
  - Undated and fragments (Box 2)
  - 1920-1950 and undated, with Jens Jensen, originals (Box 2)
  - 1928-1950 and undated, with Jens Jensen, photocopies (Box 2)
  - 1928-1950 (Box 2)
  - 1951-1958, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1959-1963, 30 folders (Box 2)
  - 1964-1967, 36 folders (Box 3)
  - 1968-1971, 20 folders (Box 4)
  - 1972-1980, 10 folders (Box 4)
  - 1981-1987 (Box 4)
- Topical file
  The Topical file series (Boxes 4-9) includes reports, clippings, minutes, and other non-correspondence material, and is arranged by subject. Materials relating to the Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation & Natural Beauty, Michigan Parks Association, Michigan state parks, and Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore form the largest bulk of the Topical file. A few outsize maps and architectural drawings have been separated and are found in the basement map cases.
  - Albion College 1958-1969 (Box 4)
  - American Society of Landscape Architects (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor (Mich.) planning (Box 4)
  - Beautification (Box 4)
  - Billboard control 1961-1967 (Box 4)
  - Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation & Natural Beauty 1966-1968
    - Agendas and minutes, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Basic national policy for landscaping of federal roads (Box 5)
    - Draft reports (Box 5)
    - Highway beautification, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Highway Subcommittee (Box 5)
    - Horvath study of I-94 (Washtenaw County, Mich.) (Box 5)
    - Pleasure Driving Subcommittee (Box 5)
    - Published reports (Box 5)
    - Reports submitted to committee (Box 5)
    - Scenic Roads Conference December 1967
      - Papers presented (Box 5)
      - Planning (Box 5)
      - Summaries (Box 5)
    - Scenic Roads Subcommittee (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Concord Township (Mich.), zoning dispute 1968 (Box 5)
  - Conservation education
    - Ann Arbor (Mich.) 1963-1966 (Box 5)
    - General 1959-1969, undated, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - School site planning 1962-1966, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Gillette Nature Center and Hoffmaster State Park 1967-1980 (Box 6)
    (see also outsize unbound material)
  - Governor's Conference on Natural Beauty 1965 (Box 6)
  - Governor's Special Commission on Urban Problems 1967 (Box 6)
  - Grand Mere (Berrien County, Mich.) development controversy 1966-1969 (Box 6)
  - Great Lakes shoreline (Box 6)
  - Hiawatha National Forest (Box 6)
  - Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority 1969-1979 (Box 6)
  - Huron River Recreation Resource Study Group 1966 (Box 6)
  - Huron River Watershed Council 1968-1970 (Box 6)
  - Huron River Watershed Intergovernmental Committee 1964 (Box 6)
  - Huron River miscellanea (Box 6)
  - Isle Royale National Park wilderness proposal 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Jens Jensen and The Clearing 1946-1961, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Keep Michigan Beautiful 1963-1970, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Land and Water Conservation Fund 1963-1968, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Landscape design lectures 1961 (Box 6)
  - McCormick Experimental Forest 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - Mayor's Conference on Natural Beauty in Ann Arbor 1966 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Botanical Club 1951, 1963-1968, undated (Box 6)
  - Michigan Conservation Commission/Dept. of Conservation
    - Agendas, etc. 1959-1964, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Organization/Reorganization (Box 6)
    - State lands 1959-1962 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous reports, etc (Box 6)
  - Michigan Dept. of Conservation Nature and Conservation Camp 1934 (Box 6)
  - Michigan homes and gardens 1929 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Horticultural Society 1932-1933 (Box 7)
  - Michigan national wildlife refuge wilderness proposals 1967-1969 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Natural Areas Council 1953-1975, undated (Box 7)
  - Michigan Natural Resources Council 1956-1969, undated (Box 7)
  - Michigan Parks Association
    - Annual Reports 1960-1969 (Box 7)
    - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 7)
    - Meeting notices 1959-1975, undated (Box 7)
    - Membership lists 1960-1970, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Minutes of meetings 1959-1972, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Newsletter 1963-1970 (Box 7)
    - Officers (Box 7)
    - Miscellanea (Box 7)
  - Michigan Parks Foundation (Box 7)
  - Michigan Shade Tree Research Foundation 1967-1968 (Box 7)
  - Michigan state parks
    - Capital outlay program 1956-1965, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Clippings (Box 7)
    - Directories and statistics 1955-1965, undated (Box 7)
    - Financing 1959-1970, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Gillette notes (Box 7)
    - Historic parks controversy 1973-1974 (Box 7)
    - Reports, etc. 1956-1969, undated, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Ten year program 1966 (Box 7)
  - Michigan United Conservation Clubs Parks and Recreation Committee 1955, 1963-1964 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Wilderness and Natural Areas Advisory Board 1972-1980, 1986, undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Mill Creek Metropark (Washtenaw County, Mich.) 1970-1973
    - Clippings (Box 8)
    - Reports, etc (Box 8)
    - Washtenaw County Metropolitan Planning Commission report 1971 (Box 8)
  - Natural areas 1959-1980, undated (Box 8)
  - Northern Great Lakes region 1963-1965 (Box 8)
  - Outdoor recreation
    - General (Box 8)
    - Michigan 1957-1969, undated, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Southeastern Michigan (Box 8)
  - Overton Park (Memphis, Tenn.) 1967-1971 (Box 8)
  - Percy J. Hoffmaster Memorial Fund 1954-1959, undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Pictured Rocks National Lakeshore 1961-1966, undated (Box 8)
  - Porcupine Mountains State Park
    - Clippings (Box 8)
    - Master plan circa 1972 (Box 8)
    - Reports, etc. 1947, 1951-1962, 1967, 1970-1972, undated, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Recreation Action Council of Michigan 1967 (Box 8)
  - Recreation bonds
    - Campaign literature 1968 (Box 8)
    - Clippings (Box 8)
    - Reports, etc. 1968-1971, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Rouge River floodplain (Dearborn, Mich.) 1973-1976, undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Scenic roads 1961-1976, undated, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore
    - Advisory Commission 1976-1978 (Box 9)
    - Bills and bill analyses 1961-1967 (Box 9)
    - Clippings (Box 9)
    - National Park Service press releases 1971-1980, undated (Box 9)
    - Reports, etc. 1959-1980, undated, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Resolutions (Box 9)
    - Testimony by Gillette 1961-1974 (Box 9)
    - Testimony by others 1961-1968 (Box 9)
  - Sylvania Recreation Area
    - Clippings (Box 9)
    - Management plan draft 1969 (Box 9)
    - Reports, etc. 1963-1971, undated (Box 9)
    - Transcript of meeting 1970 (Box 9)
  - U.S. Highway 2 reconstruction (Mackinac County, Mich.) 1976-1977 (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County (Mich.) miscellanea (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County (Mich.) parks (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County (Mich.) Planning Commission 1960-1962 (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County (Mich.) Recreation Advisory Council 1969-1972 (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County (Mich.) Parks and Recreation Commission
    - Background papers (Box 9)
    - Minutes, agendas, and memoranda 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County (Mich.) Parks Committee 1966 (Box 9)
  - Westacres Housing Project (Walled Lake, Mich.) 1935-1945 (Box 9)
  - White House Conference on Natural Beauty 1965-1966 (Box 9)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (Box 10) contains chiefly photos of Gillette at various ceremonies and meetings in the 1960s, but also includes earlier pictures of Gillette family members and homes, two albums from the 1910s, and an album of Michigan state park scenes from the 1930s.
  - Albums, Family and friends 1915-1920, 2 volumes (Box 10)
  - Awards (Box 10)
  - Citizens' Advisory Committee on Recreation & Natural Beauty 1966-1968 (Box 10)
  - Family (Box 10)
  - Gillette Nature Center dedication 1976, 1 volumes (Box 10)
  - Homes (Ann Arbor, Dimondale, Lansing, Traverse City, Mich., and Highland Park, Ill.) (Box 10)
  - Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority (Box 10)
  - Lansing: Altman Miller Co. circa 1900 (Box 10)
  - Michigan state parks
    - Album 1933-1934 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Park Washtenaw of Lyndon dedication 1966 (Box 10)
  - Portraits
    - Formal (Box 10)
    - Informal (Box 10)
  - Square House project (Box 10)
  - Walker Tavern (Cambridge Junction, Mich.) (Box 10)
  - Westacres Housing Project and other landscape architecture projects (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Negatives (Box 10)
- Audio tape cassettes
  The Audio tape cassettes series (Box 10) contains tapes of oral history interviews for which transcripts are found in Box 1. The tapes and transcripts are numbered 1-6 and 16-33 (with some discrepancies). There is no information about whether tapes 7-15 ever existed. The collection includes tapes but no transcripts for tapes 6 and 32/33, and transcripts but no tapes for tapes 3-4.
  - Oral history interviews 1971-1972 (Box 10)
    (tapes numbered 1-2, 5-6, 16A/B, 16C/D, 16E/F, 17-29, 29C, 30, 31 (2 different tapes), and 32/33)
    (see Box 1 for transcripts)
- Architectural drawings
  - Barton Hills (Mich.) residence, 5 drawings (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Children's playground at Madison (Wis.), by Jens Jensen 1945 (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Gillette Nature Center (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Jackson Park (Chicago, Ill.) plan 1965 (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
- Maps
  - Fort Custer Recreation Area (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority parkway study (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Isle Royale National Park wilderness proposal (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Mill Creek Metropark (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Proposed park areas in Baraga and Keweenaw Counties (Mich.) (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Rouge River floodplain (Dearborn, Mich.) (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore, 7 maps (Map-case 23, Folder 1)
  - Waterloo Project tour (Map-case 23, Folder 1)